"What Is the Best Statin Cholesterol-Lowering Drug?"
No fewer than 13 Nobel Prizes
have been awarded
to scientists
researching cholesterol,
culminating in a constellation
of new cholesterol-lowering
modalities.
Let me simplify.
Here’s your liver,
a blood vessel,
and bit of your intestine.
Our liver can make cholesterol
from scratch
through a long series
of reactions,
I’ve shown just two here,
which can then be packaged
and end up as LDL
in our bloodstream
to deliver cholesterol
throughout the body.
Now, we don’t want
to have too much,
as it can lodge
in our artery walls,
become oxidized,
and trigger inflammation
that can lead
to atherosclerotic plaque
and kill us.
So, our liver
also has LDL receptors
that pull LDL out of the blood
and dispose of the cholesterol
through our bile
by dumping it
into our digestive tract,
presuming our intestines will
be packed with dietary fiber
that will trap it
and ultimately flush it away.
But if the cholesterol
doesn’t get trapped,
it can be reabsorbed
and get repackaged as LDL
and re-enter our bloodstream.
The same if we eat
a bunch of cholesterol.
But the most important
dietary determinant
of cholesterol
is saturated fat.
That reduces the number
of LDL receptors;
so, more LDL stays in our blood.
Okay, stick with me.
There’s also a protein
called PCSK9 made in our liver
that helps break down
LDL receptors.
I did a video
about longevity syndromes,
where people who have
a faulty PCSK9 gene
luckily leading
to more LDL receptors
and a 90% drop
in heart disease risk.
We can also boost
our number of LDL receptors
to pull more LDL
out of our blood
by cutting down
on saturated fat intake,
but where do drugs come in?
Well, we can cut down
on cholesterol production
by blocking formation
here or here.
That’s where statins come in
or a new kid on the block
called bempedoic acid.
We could also block
the absorption and re-absorption
of cholesterol
with a drug called ezetimibe.
Or, we can block
the production of PCSK9,
or the activity of PCSK9,
so that we can maintain
our LDL receptors
to pull more LDL
out of our blood.
These PCSK9 inhibitors
cost about $6,000 a year.
Inclisiran is more like $10,000
for the first year.
And a combo of bempedoic acid
and ezetimibe
is about $5,000 a year,
whereas statins are typically
free with insurance,
and even out of pocket could
just be like 50 bucks a year,
especially since you can take
the two long-acting ones,
atorvastatin and rosuvastatin,
every other day
and cut the cost in half.
You can see why statins
are the first-line treatment
and have been
for nearly 40 years.
We actually just lost Dr. Endo,
who discovered
the first statin.
Microbes are constantly at war
with each other.
We look to fungus
like penicillin
for compounds
that kill bacteria,
and we look to bacteria
to find antifungal drugs.
Since some microbes rely
on cholesterol-like sterols,
he was hoping to find
some other microbe
that produced an anti-sterol
production compound,
and after years looking
at approximately 6,000
different microbes,
in 1972,
he came across this one,
a blue-green mold that produced
something that worked.
If he had given up
after 5,000 attempts,
then millions more people
may have died prematurely
in the ensuing decades.
If you are going to start
a statin, which one’s best?
There are seven on the market,
lowering LDL levels
from about 20% to 60%
based on brand and dose.
In terms of comparative
effectiveness and safety
for primary prevention,
atorvastatin and rosuvastatin
were most effective
in reducing
cardiovascular disease events,
while atorvastatin appeared
to have the best safety profile.
No wonder atorvastatin
became the best-selling drug
of all time,
raking in more
than a hundred billion dollars
as Lipitor before it went off
patent in 2011.